<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Admonitions by the Supreame Councell of the Confederat Catholicks of Ireand [sic] to all His Majesties faithfull loyall subjects of the three Kingdomes of England, Ireland, and Scotland against a Solemn League and Covenant framed by the malignant partie in the Parliament of England : as also against a declaration of the English Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament.</title>
            <author>Confederate Catholics. Supreme Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A593A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A598</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11171</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12093302</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12093302</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 754:20, 754:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Admonitions by the Supreame Councell of the Confederat Catholicks of Ireand [sic] to all His Majesties faithfull loyall subjects of the three Kingdomes of England, Ireland, and Scotland against a Solemn League and Covenant framed by the malignant partie in the Parliament of England : as also against a declaration of the English Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Confederate Catholics. Supreme Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Bourke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>VVaterford [Waterford] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>26 Ian. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A Solemne League and Covenant for reformation and defence of religion. London: Printed for Edward Husbands, Octob. 9, 1643 (p. [7]-12) and A declaration of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament shewing the present design now on foot ... for a cessation of armes ... London: Printed for Io. VVright ... Octob. 2, 1645 (p. [15-22]) have special title pages.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Ireland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:53932:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53932:1"/>
                  <p>ADMONITIONS BY THE SVPREAME COVNCELL OF THE CONFEDERAT CATHOLICKS OF IREAND, To all his Majeſties faithfull Loyall Subjects of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againſt a <hi>Solemne League</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> framed by the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant partie in the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As alſo againſt a Declaration of the English Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed by Command of the ſaid Supreame Councell, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>VVaterford</hi> by <hi>Thomas Bourke,</hi> 26. <hi>Ian.</hi> 1643.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="order">
                  <pb facs="tcp:53932:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53932:2"/>
                  <head>BY THE SVPREAME COVNCELL OF THE CONFEDERAT CATHOLICKS of IRELAND.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſince the laſt generall Aſſembly of the ſaid <hi>Confederat Catholicks</hi> held at the City of <hi>VVaterford</hi> ſeene a Solemne <hi>league</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> framed by the <hi>Malignant party</hi> in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and by them procured to be ſworne by ſuch of his Majeſties Subjects as they could ſeduce in the kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſent likewiſe into ſome parts of this kingdome, to infect others, wherein are contained reſolutions ſo deſtructive to the Profeſſors of the <hi>Catholicke Faith</hi> in generall, to his Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects and this Nation in particular, that wee ſhould betray the truſt repoſed in us, had wee not given timely notice thereof to the ſaid <hi>Confederat Catholicks,</hi> whereby they may bee forewarned of their utter extirpation intended, ſo farre as may lie in the power of the ſaid <hi>Malignant party,</hi> to which end we have cauſed the ſaid ſolemne <hi>league</hi> &amp; <hi>Covenant</hi> to be printed, in which all Chriſtian Princes and their good Subjects may obſerve, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency of the ſaid rebellious incendiaries being not ſatisfied to have withdrawne themſelves from their allegeance, and to have raiſed armes againſt ſo gracious a King, but alſo thereby endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to poyſon the mindes of the faithfull Subjects of other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with their diſloyalty, inſerting in the preamble of that <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Covenant</hi> theſe words <hi>(calling to minde the treacherous and bloudy plotts, Conſpiracies, attempts, and practiſes of the enemies of God against the true Religion and profeſſors thereof in all places)</hi> not confining them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the three kingdomes of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> And in the percloſe of that <hi>Covenant,</hi> adding theſe words <hi>(moſt humbly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53932:3"/>beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by his Holy Spirit, for this end and to bleſſe our deſignes and proceedings with ſuch ſucceſſe as may be deliverance and ſafety to his people, and encouragement to other Chriſtian Churches groaning under, or in danger of the yoake of Antichriſtian tyranny to joyne in the ſame or the like aſſociation and Covenant.)</hi> By which all the world may evidently ſee; how far they deſire their treaſon againſt Monarchie to be ſpred, by ſuch and the like <hi>Covenant</hi> and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſe, and in other the partes of that oath, bounded to the limitts of the three Kingdomes of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland, they ſweare to a reformation (as they tearme it) of Religion in</hi> England, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and to endeavour to bring the Church of God in the ſaid three kingdomes to uniformitie in Religion and Confeſsion of Faith, and that they shall in like manner without reſpect of perſons endeavour the extirpation of Popery and Prelacy,</hi> as hereafter in the oath is more at large expreſſed, whereby the <hi>Catholicks</hi> of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> may plainely forſee what rigour they are to expect, and how they ſtand forewarned to prepare themſelves for a defenſive and offenſive warre againſt the ſaid <hi>Malignant party,</hi> or failing therein will be driven to quit all they can call theirs in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> How vaine it is for any his Majeſties <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Subjects</hi> to hope for mercy, at the hands of that party, when the generall words <hi>(without reſpect of perſons,)</hi> have left no exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for any, but would extirpate all without diſtinction of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or difference of quality, contrary to the law of <hi>Nations,</hi> and when their malice is ſo high ſwolne that they aſſume Regall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ſo farre as to preſume to proclaime warre againſt us, their fellow Subjects, even in the beſt times of their loyaltie, and that without any relation to his Majeſties allowance. So as wee are to expect no peace untill they bee reclaimed, and when they ſo deſpiſe the power and intereſt of his Majeſtie, and of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Catholicke</hi> Subjects of the three kingdomes, as that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve likewiſe the extirpation of <hi>Archbishops, Bishops, Prelats</hi> &amp; all other dignitaries of what religion ſoever, we therefore being bound by the oath of aſſociation ſolemnely by us taken to preſerve our <hi>Religion,</hi> maintaine the priviledges and juſt prerogatives of our Sacred Soveraigne, and defend the liberties of our Countrey, obſerving by the ſiniſter and un godly practiſes of the ſaid <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53932:3"/>party</hi> that the whole ſcope of their wicked intentions is to extirpate the <hi>Catholicke Religion,</hi> and the profeſſors thereof in the ſaid three kingdomes, deſtroy Monarchie, deprive our ſaid Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne of his juſt prerogatives, and baniſh or put to death all ſuch of his Majeſties Subjects, aſwell <hi>Protestants,</hi> as <hi>Catholicks</hi> who will not conforme themſelves to their doctrine, ſo erronious and deſtructive to the rights of Monarchie, in diſcharge of our ſaid oath, for the preſervation of our <hi>Religion,</hi> in obſervance of our Loyalty to our ſaid Sacred Soveraigne, the maintenance of his Prerogatives, the defence of our lives, liberties and eſtates, and lives liberties &amp; eſtates of all his Majeſties well affected Subjects in his ſaid three Kingdomes, doe earneſtly deſire them upon view &amp; peruſall of the ſaid <hi>Covenant</hi> ſeriouſly to conſider the dangerous and foule intentions of the ſaid evill projectors, &amp; to make full &amp; timely preparation for the ſafety of themſelves and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and doe alſo deſire all <hi>Catholicke Princes</hi> &amp; their good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, aſſecting the preſervation of their <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp; the Rights of Soveraignty, to conſider how far they are concerned in that ſo bloudy &amp; impious a reſolution, &amp; to find a timely &amp; fit remedy to be applied to ſo contagious a deſigne, which the ſaid <hi>Malignant party</hi> would invite the Subjects of all <hi>Christian Princes</hi> to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:53932:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53932:4"/>
                  <p>A SOLEMNE LEAGVE AND COVENANT FOR REFORMATION AND DEFENCE OF RELIGION The honour and happineſſe of the KING, and the peace and ſafety of the three Kingdomes, of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alſo two ſpeciall orders</hi> viz.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Concerning the taking of the <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> in all <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Chappells</hi> in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>VVestminſter,</hi> upon the next <hi>Lords day</hi> in the afternoone.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Concerning divers <hi>Lòrds, Knights, Gentlemen, Colonells, Officers, Souldiours,</hi> and others, that are deſirous to meet this preſent <hi>Friday</hi> in the afternoone at <hi>Margarets VVeſtminster,</hi> and to take the ſaid <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Ier. 50.5.</hi>
                        </bibl> Come let us ioyne our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall Covenant, that ſhall not be forgotten.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Prov. 25.5.</hi>
                        </bibl> Take away the wicked from before the King, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2 Chro. 15.15.</hi>
                        </bibl> And all Iudah reioyced at the Oath, for they had ſworne with all their heart, and ſought him with their whole deſire, and he was found of them, and the Lord gave them reſt round about.</p>
                  </q>
                  <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Die Sabbathi,</hi> 30. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1643.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>It is this day ordered by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament. That this Covenant and Orders bee forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with printed and publiſhed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>H. Elſings Cl. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London, Printed for</hi> Edward Husbands, <hi>Octob.</hi> 9. 1643.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="order">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53932:5"/>
                  <head>Die Lunae <hi>25.</hi> Septemb. <hi>1643.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is this day ordered by the <hi>Commons</hi> now aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Miniſters in all the <hi>Parish Churches</hi> and <hi>Chappells</hi> of <hi>London, VVeſtminſter,</hi> Suburbs and Liberties, and in all Pariſhes within the Bills of Mortality, doe read the ſolemne League and Covenant on Wedneſday next, being the day of publicke humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation; And doe explane it, and urge the ground and neceſſity of it, and exhort the people to the cheerfull taking of it, and that the ſeverall Inhabitants and Pariſhioners of the ſeverall and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Pariſhes arforeſaid, and Students of the Innes of Court doe take the ſaid League and Covenant on the Lords day next in the afternoone: And that notice hereof be given to my Lord Mayor, and his Lordſhip deſired to give timely notice hereof to the places aforeſaid. The Miniſters are likewiſe to give notice, that the Comiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> now here doe take it here.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Elſinge. Cler. Parl. D. Cem.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>Die Sabbathi, <hi>30.</hi> Sept. <hi>1643.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHereas divers Lords, Knights, Gentlemen and divers Colonells, Officers and Souldiours, and others now reſiding in the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>VVeſtminster</hi> and within the line of Communication, are deſirous to meere at Saint <hi>Margarets</hi> Church at <hi>VVestminster</hi> on Friday next, to take the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne League and Covenant for Reformation, and defence of the honour and happineſſe of the King, and the peace and ſafety of the three Kingdomes, of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And whereas divers of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Nation, are deſirous likewiſe to meet at the ſame time and place and divers Miniſters who have no charge within the ſaid limits to take the ſaid Covenant.</p>
                  <p>It is this day ordered by the Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; That <hi>M. Carrill</hi> of <hi>Lincolus Inne</hi> be deſired to preach on Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day next in the forenoone, to thoſe that ſhall ſo meet, for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſaid Covenant; And a Parchment Rolle with the ſaid Covenant written therein, ſhall be prepared for every one that take the ſaid Covenant to ſubſcribe his name and Colonell <hi>Long</hi> and <hi>M. Iohn Browne</hi> members of the ſaid Houſe, are to ſee the names ſubſcribed accordingly: And this order is appointed to be printed and publiſhed forthwith.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Elſinge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="covenant">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53932:5"/>
                  <head>A ſolemne League and Covenant for Reformation and defence of Religion, the honour and happineſſe of the King, and the peace and ſafety of the three Kingdomes of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</head>
                  <p>WE Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Commons of all ſorts in the Kingdomes of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the providence of God living under one King, and being of one reformed religion, having before our eyes the glory of God, and the advancement of the Kingdome of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the honour and happineſſe of the Kings Majeſtie and his poſterity, and the true publicke liberty, ſafety and peace of the kingdomes, wherein every ones private condition is included, <hi>and calling to mind the treacherous and bloudy plotts, conſpiracies, attempts, and practiſes of the enemies of God againſt the true Religion, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors thereof in all places,</hi> eſpecially in theſe three kingdomes, ever ſince the reformation of Religion, and how much their rage, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and preſumption, are of late, and at this time increaſed and exerciſed, whereof the deplorable ſtate of the Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the diſtreſſed eſtate of the Church and kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and the dangerous eſtate of the Church and kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> are preſent and publicke teſtimonies. We have now at laſt after other meanes of ſupplication, remonſtrance, Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſufferings, for the preſervation of our ſelves and our Religion, from utter ruine and deſtruction, according to the commendable practiſe of theſe kingdomes in former times, and the example of Gods people in other Nations; after mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, reſolved and determined to enter into a mutuall and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne League and Covenant, wherein we all ſubſcribe, &amp; each one of us for himſelfe, with our hands lifted up to the moſt High God, doe ſweare.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly through the grace of God, endeavour in our ſeverall places and callings, the preſervation of the reformed Religion in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in doctrine worſhip, diſcipline and government, againſt our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53932:6"/>common enemyes, <hi>the reformation of Religion in the kingdomes of England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in doctrine, worſhip, diſcipline, and governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches. And ſhall endeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three kingdomes to the neereſt conjunction and uniformity in religion, confeſſion of Faith, Forme of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, directory for worſhip, and Cathechiſing, that wee and all our poſterity after us, may as brethren live in Faith and love, and the Lord may delight to dwell in the middeſt of us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That we ſhall in the like manner <hi>without reſpect of perſons, endeavour the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, that is,</hi> Church-governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chauncellours and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries, Deanes, Chapters, Archdeacons, and all other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall officers depending on that Hierarchie, ſuperſtition, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, ſchiſme, prophaneneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe, leſt we partake in other mens ſinnes, and thereby be in danger to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of their plagues, and that the Lord may bee one, and his Name one in the three kingdomes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We ſhall with the ſame ſincerity, reallity, and conſtancy in our ſeverall vocations, endeavour with our eſtates and lives, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to preſerve the rights and priviledges of Parliaments, and the liberties of the kingdomes; and to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties perſon and authority in the preſervation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the true Religion and Liberties of the kingdomes, that the world may beare witneſſe with our conſciences of our Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, and that we have no thoughts or intentions to diminiſh his Majeſties juſt power and greatneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Wee ſhall alſo with all faithfulneſſe endeavour the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of all ſuch as have beene, or ſhall be incendiaties, malignants or evill inſtruments, by hindering the reformation of Religion, dividing the King from his people, or one of the kingdomes from another, or making any faction or parties amongſt the people, contrary to this League and Covenant, that they may be brought to publicke triall, and receive co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndigne puniſhment, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of their offences ſhall require or deſerve, or the ſupreame Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories of both kingdomes reſpectively, or others having po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer from them for that effect, ſhall judge convenient.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53932:6"/> 5. And whereas the happineſſe of a bleſſed peace betweene theſe kingdomes, denyed in former times to our progenitors, is by the good providence of God granted unto us, and hath beene lately concluded, and ſetled by both Parliaments, we ſhall each of us according to our place and intereſt endeavour that they may remaine conjoyned in a firme peace, and union to all poſterity: And that Iuſtice may be done upon the wilfull oppoſers thereof, in manner expreſſed in the precedent Article.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. We ſhall alſo according to our places and callings in this common cauſe of Religion, liberty and peace of the kingdomes, aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into this League, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, in the maintaining and purſuing thereof, and ſhall not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our ſelves directly nor indirectly by whoſoever combination, perſwaſion or terrour, to be divided from this bleſſed union and conjunction, whether to make defection to the contrary parts or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable indifferency or neutrality in this cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the kingdomes, and honour of the King, but ſhall all the dayes of our lives zealouſly and conſtantly continue therein, againſt all oppoſition, and promote the ſame according to our power againſt all letts and impediments whatſoever; and what wee are not able ourſelves to ſuppreſſe or overcome, wee ſhall reveale and make knowne that it may be timely prevented, all which, wee ſhall doe as in the ſight of God.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe theſe kingdomes are guilty of many ſins and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations againſt God, and his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, as is too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, by our preſent diſtreſſes and dangers, the fruits thereof; we profeſſe and declare before God, and the world, our unfayned deſire to bee humbled for our owne ſins, and for the ſins of theſe kingdomes, eſpecially, that wee have not as wee ought valued the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpell, that wee have not labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the purity and power thereof, and that wee have not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to receive Chriſt in our hearts, nor to walke worthy of him in our lives, which are the cauſes of other ſins and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions ſo much abounding amongſt us; And our true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained purpoſe, deſire, and endeavour for our ſelves, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers under our power and charge, both in publicke and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, in all duties we owe to God and man, to amend our lives,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53932:7"/>and each one to goe before other in the example of a reall Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the Lord may turne away his wrath and heavy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Churches and kingdomes in truth and peace, and this Covenant wee make in the preſence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true intention to performe the ſame as we ſhall anſwer at that great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall bee diſcloſed; moſt humbly beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by his Holy Spirit for this end, and to bleſſe our deſires and proceedings, with ſuch ſucceſſe as may bee deliverance and ſafety to his people, <hi>and encouragement to other Chriſtian Churches, groaning under, or in danger of the yoake of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Tyranny, to joyne in the ſame, or like</hi> Aſſociation and Covenant, to the glory of God, the enlargement of the Kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt, and the peace and tranquillity of Chriſtian Kingdomes and Commonwealths.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:53932:7"/>
                  <head>BY THE SVPREAME COVNCELL OF THE CONFEDERAT CATHOLICKS of IRELAND.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He enſueing Declaration having come to our hands ſoone after the receſſe of the late Generall Aſſembly of the <hi>Confederate Catholicks</hi> held at <hi>VVaterford,</hi> wee thought fit for the better publiſhing thereof, in all the parts of this kingdome, that the ſame ſhould bee printed, whereby his Majeſties good Subjects, may evidently ſee, what inſolent expreſſions are therein contained, againſt his Majeſties power, and proceedings, againſt his Majeſties <hi>Catholicke Subjects,</hi> &amp; againſt all well minded <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that labour to ſettle a right underſtanding, betwixt his Majeſtie &amp; his Subjects of this kingdome: they take upon them to Cenſure his Majeſty for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing perſons affected to <hi>Religion,</hi> and putting into their places men <hi>Popishly</hi> addicted, or in plaine <hi>English</hi> for diſplacing <hi>Sir VVilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Parſons,</hi> and appointing <hi>Sir Henry Tichborne</hi> one of the Iuſtices, and of the reſt it is apparant whom they meane, they take notice that in his Majeſties Commiſſion ſent hither to receive the <hi>Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances</hi> of his people, ſome of the Commiſſioners were <hi>Papiſts,</hi> there being none named of ſuch as they intend thereby, but the Earle of <hi>Clanrikard,</hi> (whom it ſeemeth they thinke) either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of that honour, or unfit to be truſted: they ſay, that the <hi>Catholicks</hi> of this kingdome are reduced to ſuch Neceſſity, that they devoure and eate one another, which (praiſe be to God) is moſt falſe, our markets being in moſt places, as well ſupplied as at any time before: and where thoſe here of the State, that did adhere, to the malignant party in <hi>England,</hi> reſolved to deſtroy this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by famine, and to that purpoſe adviſed all the Cornes, in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53932:8"/>march of the forces, to bee burned, and accordingly very much Corne was Burned, many thouſands of the ſaid forces by the juſt Iudgment of God periſhed within their Garriſons in ſundry parts of this kingdome for want of victualls, they laboured to hinder any Ceſſation with the ſaid <hi>Catholicks,</hi> urging that the deſigne thereof did ariſe firſt from them, (an objection proper to ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt their King,) ought not a dutifull people to petition for redreſſe of their grievances to their Prince, they affirme that the raiſing of Armes by this Nation, (which they Call Rebellion,) was without provocation, but reſolutions of extirpating, the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Religion,</hi> and the profeſſors thereof, in this kingdome, will be proved, not onely by teſtimony of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> but even of many <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and then all the world they hope will witneſſe with them the juſtneſſe, and neceſſity of this war: and though they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of ſucceſſe, and inſinuate, that the <hi>Catholicks</hi> failing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile by ſtrength, have recourſe to Craft. Yet it is well knowne that in moſt Conflicts the loſſe was greater of the other ſide: the Authors of this Declaration are not ſatisfied to have overbuſied themſelves and aſſumed Regall Power in <hi>England,</hi> but hereby let the <hi>Counſell</hi> of <hi>State</hi> here, know, how highly they have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they acquainted them not with the intention of a Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Armes, and let them alſo know, that they repreſented the wants of the Armies here unto the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> with much Craft to have a ground, wherewith to collour the Ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as if his Majeſties Commiſſion were not ſufficient to juſtifie their proceedings therein, and conclude with this inference, that the forces here by meanes of this Ceſſation, will find opportunity to joyne with the <hi>Popish</hi> party in <hi>England,</hi> for their greater ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, by all which it is evident, that if the uſurped Regall power of thoſe incendiaries, can have influence on <hi>Ireland,</hi> that none with, or without his Majeſties Commiſſion ſhall ſtand juſtified, but ſuch as adhere to them and their Rebellion, and forſake their Loyalty, and obedience to his Majeſties Commands.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53932:8"/>
                  <p>A DECLARATION OF THE LORDS AND COMMONS ASSEMBLED IN PARLIAMENT.</p>
                  <p>Shewing the preſent deſigne now on foot (by vertue of a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Comiſſion from his Majeſtie) for a ceſſation of Armes, or treaty of peace with the <hi>Rebells</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> now they are brought to ſuch a low condition, that they are inforced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure and eate one another, in ſome parts of that kingdome: And by what Popiſh inſtruments and miniſters in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at the Court, the ſaid deſigne is, and hath been carried on, perſons of great truſt, eminent for their affection or Religion and hatred of the <hi>Rebells</hi> being diſplaced, and men Popiſhly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted put in their offices: all ſerving for the better introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Popery, and extirpation of the true Proteſtant Religion in that and other of his Majeſties dominions.</p>
                  <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Die Sabbathi</hi> 30. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1643.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ordered by the Lords and Commons aſsembled in Parliament that this declaration shall be forthwith printed and published.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Io. Browne Cler. Parlment.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>London, Printed for <hi>Io. VVright</hi> in old Baily, <hi>Octob.</hi> 2. 1645.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="declaration">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53932:9"/>
                  <head>A DECLARATION OF THE LORDS AND COMMONS ASSEMBLED IN PARLIAMENT,</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is evident to all the world that this late hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Rebellion of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any colour or pretext of provocation profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly and boldly ayme at the deſtruction of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, the rejecting of the lawes of <hi>England,</hi> and the extirpation of the <hi>Brittish</hi> inhabitants out of that kingdome; ſo it is no leſſe manifeſt that this Parliament of <hi>England</hi> (to whom his Majeſty hath left the managing of the warre againſt thoſe rebels) hath taken the troubles of <hi>Ireland</hi> to heart with that reſentment and compaſſion as may evidence their zeale to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, their love to their diſtreſt Countreymen and brethren there, in theſe times, when the <hi>Ieſuiticall</hi> practiſes have caſt <hi>England</hi> into wofull diſtractions, and unnaturall warre, notwithſtanding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53932:9"/>which, the reducing of <hi>Ireland</hi> hath ſtill beene a chiefe part of the care of this Parliament, And God hath beene pleaſed to bleſſe our endeavours with ſuch ſucceſſe as that thoſe furious bloud, thirſty <hi>Papiſts</hi> have beene in the carrier of their crueltie, ſome part of the <hi>Protestant</hi> bloud which at firſt was ſpilt like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon the ground hath beene revenged, their maſſacres, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and famiſhings, have by a divine retaliation beene repayde into their boſome; And the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> party hath been erected to that condition of ſtrenght and hope, that their enemies are conſtrayned (diſtruſting their forces) to have recourſe to their craft &amp; policies, and therefore by their ſubtill Agents at Court, and their active inſtruments elſewhere, have beene endeavoring now of along time to make our Armies in <hi>Ireland</hi> diſaffected to the Parliament, what by occaſion of their wants not ſo readily ſupplyed as their neede required, what by miſuſing them with theſe unhappy differences fallen in here betweene <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>People,</hi> labouring by that meanes to devide thoſe forces into factions, to the end the maine worke they have in hand might be neglected, which is the proſecution of the warre againſt the Rebels, &amp; ſo far brought low in ſome partes of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that if they can bee depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the benefit of this Harveſt, they are not likely to ſee the next Summer. And therefore the Rebels finding that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the diſtractions here occaſioning the ſlowneſſe &amp; ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſupplyes, yet they themſelves are in a farre worſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being in want of moſt things neceſſary, not onely for the maintayning of a warre, but even of life the judgement of God being remarkeable upon them in this, that as their bloudy and treacherous Religion made them inhumanely cruell in ſhedding the proteſtants bloud, ſo now the famine amongſt many of them hath made them unnaturally, and Canniball-like eate and feede one upon another. Therefore that they may have time to expect from their friends abroad new ſupplyes both of victuals and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and may without moleſtation reape the fruite of this harveſt, they have laboured a treaty for a Ceſſation, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of theirs doth no leſſe ayme at the overthrow of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Proteſtants in that kingdome then their treacherous ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Armes at the firſt did intend the deſtruction of them all; for their Ceſſation and hoſtility, their warre and peace are alike
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53932:10"/>to be eſteemed of, and with thoſe that neyther in peace nor warre keepe any faith, it is beſt to be in perpetuall defiance: Therefore the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled according to their continued care of that kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> doe in a ſpeciall manner take into their conſideration the condition thereof upon this occaſion of an intended Ceſſation, and ſo much the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is feared that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> forces through want of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for their Armies, may at laſt, if not relieved be perſwaded to admit of this courſe in hope thereby to procure ſome meanes for their ſubſiſting, as alſo becauſe there is too much ground to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, that if this Ceſſation ſhould be agreed unto, they might have opportunitie to joyne with the <hi>papiſt</hi> party heere for their greater ſtrenghtning. And though it were to have no influence upon this kingdome, yet the evill conſequences of it are ſo many and pernicious to <hi>Ireland,</hi> that this Parliament ſhould betray the truſt repoſed in them, if they did not declare againſt this Ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and uſe all meanes in time to make it prove abortive, And therefore they deſire that it may be obſerved and taken notice of.</p>
                  <p>Firſt from whence the Counſell and deſigne of this Ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ariſeth even from the rebels and <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves for their owne preſervation, for ſoone after they had miſſed of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to make themſelves abſolute maſters of that kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> by their treacherous ſurpriſes. And ſeeing that this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome did with moſt generous and Chriſtian reſolutions under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the charges of warre for the reliefe and recovery of <hi>Ireland,</hi> propoſitions were brought from the Rebellion the <hi>Lords Dillon</hi> &amp; <hi>Taffe</hi> at which time they were intercepted. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> reſtrayned by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the houſe of Commons: After that, they had the boldneſſe even while their hands were ſtill imbrued in the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> bloud to petition to his Majeſtie that their demands might be heard, and for this purpoſe they obtayned a Commiſſion to be ſent over in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ireland</hi> to divers perſons of quality (whereof ſome were <hi>Papiſts</hi>) to heare, receive, &amp; tranſmit to his Majeſty their demands which was done accordingly, and one Maſter <hi>Bourke,</hi> a notorious prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke <hi>Irish papist,</hi> was the chiefe ſollicitor in this buſineſſe, after this, the juſt revenging God giving daily ſucceſſe to the handfull of the <hi>Protestant</hi> forces, againſt their great numbers, ſo that by a wonderfull bleſſing from heaven they were in moſt parts put to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53932:10"/>the worſt. Then did they begin to ſet on foote an overtime for a Ceſſation of Armes, concerning which, what going and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming hath beene between the Court and the Rebels is very well knowne, and what meetings and treaties have beene held about it in <hi>Ireland</hi> by warrant of his Majeſties ample Commiſſion ſent to that effect; and what reception and countenance moſt pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke <hi>Papists</hi> negotiating the buſineſſe &amp; found at Court, and that thoſe of the State in <hi>Dublin</hi> who had ſo much Religion, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty as to diſſwade the Ceſſation were firſt diſcountenanced and at laſt put out of their places, and reſtrayned to priſon, as <hi>Sir VVi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lliam Parſons</hi> one of the Lords ſuſtices there, <hi>Sir Iohn Temple</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Rolles, Sir Adam Loftus</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Treaſurer at warres, and <hi>Sir Robert Meredith</hi> one alſo of the Councell-Table.</p>
                  <p>Secondly the Lords and Commons deſire it may be obſerved that during all theſe paſſages and negotiations the houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament were never acquainted by the ſtate of <hi>Ireland</hi> with the treaty of a Ceſſation, much leſſe was their adviſe or Counſell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, notwithſtanding that the care, and managing of the war was devolved on them both by Act of Parliament, and by his Majeſties Commiſſion under the great Seale, to adviſe, order, and diſpoſe of all things concerning the government, and defence of that kingdome, but the wants of the Army were often repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and complayned of, whereby with much craft a ground was preparing for the pretext, wherewith now they would cover the Counſell of this Ceſſation, as if nothing had drawne it on, but the extreame wants of their Armies, whereas it is evident, that the report of ſuch a treaty have beene (in a great part) the cauſe of their wants, for thereby the adventurers were diſheartned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions were ſtopped, and by the admittance to Court of the negotiators of this Ceſſation: their wicked Councell have had that influence, as to procure the intercepting of much proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which were ſent for <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo that Ships going for <hi>Ireland</hi> with victuals, and others comming from thence with commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to exchange for victuals, have beene taken by <hi>Dunkerkers</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Majeſties warrant, but alſo by <hi>English</hi> Ships commanded by <hi>Sir Iohn Pennigton</hi> under his Majeſty. And moreover the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament meſſengers ſent into ſeverall Counties with the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>Ianuary</hi> laſt for Ioanes, and contributions, have beene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53932:11"/>and impriſoned, their Money taken from them, and not one penny eyther loane or contribution hath been ſuffered to be ſent in for <hi>Ireland,</hi> from thoſe Counties which were under the power of the Kings army, while in the meane time the houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by their ordinances, declarations, &amp; ſollicitations to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London,</hi> &amp; the counties free from the terror of the Kings for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were ſtill procuring not contemptible ayde and reliefe for the diſtreſſes of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, as the Lords and Commons have reaſon to declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this plot &amp; deſigne of a Ceſſation of armes, as being treated and carryed on without their adviſe, ſo alſo, becauſe of the great prejudice which will thereby redound to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion and the encouragement, and advancement which it will give to the practiſe of <hi>Popery,</hi> when theſe rebellious <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſhall by this agreement continue and ſet up with more freedome their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worſhip, their <hi>Popish</hi> ſuperſtitions, and <hi>Romish</hi> abominations in all the places of their command, to the diſhonoring of God, the grieving of all true <hi>Protestant</hi> hearts, the diſpiſing the Lawes of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and to the provoking of the wrath of a Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, as if both kingdomes had not ſmarted enough already for this ſin, of too much connyving at, and tolerating of <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Idolatry, under pretext of Civill contracts and politick agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>In the fourth place they deſire it may be obſerved that this Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation will prove diſhonorable to the publicke faith of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it will elude and make null the acts and ordinances of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament made for the forfeyting of Rebels Lands, at the paſſing of which acts it was repreſented that ſuch a courſe would drive the Rebels to deſpayre, &amp; it prove ſo, but otherwiſe then was meant. For diſpayring of their force and courage they go about to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come us with their craft.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly what ſhall become of the many poore exiled <hi>Protestants</hi> turned out of their eſtates by this rebellion, who muſt now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue begging their bread, while the rebels ſhall enjoy their lands and houſes, And who ſhall ſecure the reſt of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their owne courage, induſtry, &amp; great charges hath kept their poſſeſſions, or by the ſucceſſe of our Armies have beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, can there be any aſſurance gotten from a perfidious enemy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53932:11"/>of a Ceſſation, from butchery, and breach of agreement, when they ſhall ſee a fit time and opportunity.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and many other conſiderations being well weighed, it will appeare evidently, that this deſigne of a Ceſſation is a deepe plot laid by the Rebells, and really invented for their own ſafety and falſely pretended to bee for the benefit of our Armies: And whereas the Lords and Commons have no certaine information, that the treaty is concluded, but are informed by ſeverall letters, that all the <hi>Protestants</hi> as well inhabitants as ſoldiors in that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, are reſolved to withſtand that proceeding, and to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on the greateſt extremities, rather then have any ſort of peace with that generation, who have ſo cruelly, in time of peace, murthered many thouſands of our Countrey-men, and laboured to extirpe the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> from amongſt them, ſo they doe believe, that theſe rumors of a Ceſſation were firſt contrived by the enemies of our Religion and peace, and by their practiſes the treaty was carried on with much ſubtility and ſollicitation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſtoppe the ſending of ſupplies from thence to our Armies, and for the cooling of the affections of thoſe who have already ſhewed their zeale to the weale of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and therefore the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meanes to defeate this their policy, and prevent the evills in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by it, is to ſettle a courſe whereby the army of <hi>Ireland</hi> may be at leaſt fenced againſt hunger and cold, for which purpoſe it is deſired, that all thoſe who are well affected to the <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> either in that or this kingdome. And all thoſe who by their adventures already made, have imbarked their particular intereſts with the publicke of that kingdome, and doe deſire a good returne of their engagements will joyne their endeavours for obviating of that neceſſity, which may be made a ſtrong argument to enforce a deſtructive Ceſſation of Armes, &amp; that they would nor through too much ſuſpition and jealouſie of it forbeare the providing of ſupplies, and ſo occaſion that inconvenience which they ought by all meanes to prevent, for by ſo doeing they will looſe all their former paines and charges, and the withholding of proviſions will gaine credit to that calumny laid againſt this kingdome, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting the armies of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and by the continuing of ſupplies, theſe forces will bee encouraged to continue the warre, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owne both their worke and ours.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53932:12"/>
                  <p> And laſtly the Rebels ſeeing aſſiſtance againſt them ſtill flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from hence muſt needs be out of hope of proſecuting or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding this their deſigne, the cry of much <hi>Proteſtant</hi> bloud, the great indigencie of many ruynate families, the danger of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion almoſt exiled out of that kingdome calls for this laſt act of piety, charity, juſtice, and policy from us, which being reſolved on letters are to bee diſpatcht to the ſeverall partes of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to encourage the Commanders and ſouldiers upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid reaſons and aſſurances, that they may not hearken to ſuch an unjuſt and deceitfull counſell, and as by their proſecuting of the warre through Gods bleſſing, they have ſucceſſe fully reſiſted the Rebels cruelty, ſo they may upon this occaſion beware they be not over reached by their crafts.</p>
                  <p>All which the Lords and Commons doe earneſtly deſire may be ſeriouſly taken into heart by all the kingdome, and that from thoſe other encouragements mentioned at large, in the ordinance of the fourteenth of <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, and ſuch as are now offered, a courſe may be taken wherby ſuch a conſtant weekely contribution may be ſetled, as will ſupply the Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> The meere neceſſity of nature which may be more punctually and ſeaſonably tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the ſeverall parts of that kingdome according to their reſpective wants, that ſo the benefit and honour of ſo pious a worke, happily begun, and ſucceſſively hitherto carryed on may not be loſt when ſo little remaynes to be done, And that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of a kingdome, the reeſtabliſhing of ſo many <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Churches, the repoſſeſſing of ſo many thouſand Chriſtians unto their eſtates may not be deſerted and let fall to the ground for a little more paines and coſt.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53932:12"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
